<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="doc-formatter.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE indicator-declaration SYSTEM "indicator-declaration.dtd">
<indicator-declaration display-name="Employment">
<syntax-version-2.8/>

	<indicator-documentation>
		<definition>
			For each year of interest, this indicator gives the total number of jobs in the selected geography. 
		</definition>
		<interpreting-results>
			If the selected geography is 'region', the indicator value will be simply the total number of jobs 
			in the region for that year; if the selected 
			geography is 'grid', then the indicator value will be the number of jobs placed in each grid cell for the given year.
			At geographies below 
			the region as a whole, this indicator shows the concentrations of employment.
		</interpreting-results>
		<related-indicators>
			This is related to <a href="employment_density.xml">Employment density</a>.  However, this indicator gives the total number of jobs in the selected geography,
			while Employment density gives the number of jobs per acre of nonresidential land.
		</related-indicators>
		<specification>
			If the selected geography is the entire region, we simply count the total number of jobs for the given year (including the number of unplaced jobs, if any).  
			If the selected geography is 'grid', we count the total number of jobs placed in each grid cell for each year. 
			For the general case, we count the total number of jobs in the grid cells that are contained in each geography.
		</specification>
		<limitations>
			The employment and other data available for running UrbanSim may well not include information about the informal economy.
			In that case UrbanSim would not take  employment in the informal economy into account.
		</limitations>
		<how-modeled>
			When the geography is the entire region, the value of this indicator is exogenous (in other words, it isn't modeled by Urbansim).
			This is because the total regional employment is
			specified by external control totals for each year.  When the geography is smaller, the value of this indicator is modeled 
			by UrbanSim itself, since UrbanSim models where jobs locate within the region.
		</how-modeled>
		<source-evolution-examples>
			This indicator was originally written by the UrbanSim group.
		</source-evolution-examples>
		
<display-format>
<units>jobs</units>
<number digits="0"/>
</display-format>

</indicator-documentation>

<source>
<a href="http://trondheim.cs.washington.edu/cgi-bin/trac.cgi/browser/urbansim/gridcell/number_of_jobs.py">urbansim.gridcell.number_of_jobs</a>
</source>

</indicator-declaration>
