<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="doc-formatter.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE indicator-declaration SYSTEM "indicator-declaration.dtd">
<indicator-declaration display-name="Greenhouse Gas Emissions from Vehicle Travel">
<syntax-version-2.8/>

<indicator-documentation>

<definition>
This indicator gives the estimated greenhouse gas emissions produced by vehicles traveling from the selected geography in a given year. 
</definition>

<interpreting-results>
Please see <a href="#how-modeled">How Modeled</a> for information on interpreting the results from this indicator.
</interpreting-results>

<principal-uses>
This indicator is useful for both evaluative and diagnostic purposes.
</principal-uses>

<specification>
The value of this indicator is calculated as the 
<a href="vehicle_miles_traveled.xml">vehicle miles traveled</a> multipled by 
the coefficient for CO<sub>2</sub> pounds emitted per vehicle mile traveled. 
This coefficient, 0.915, was obtained from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) 
website about emission facts. The website was accessed on 5/8/2006. Please see 
<a href="http://www.epa.gov/otaq/consumer/f00013.htm">http://www.epa.gov/otaq/consumer/f00013.htm</a>. 
As stated on the website, the coefficient is based on "fleetwide average in-use fuel economy of 21.5 
miles per gallon (mpg) for passenger cars...as reported in the 19th edition 
of the "Transportation Energy Data Book," prepared for the U.S. Department of Energy."
</specification>

<related-indicators>
<p><a href="vehicle_miles_traveled.xml">Vehicle miles traveled</a> gives the total vehicle miles traveled with an origin in the specified geography. It is used in the calculation.</p>
<p><a href="vehicle_miles_traveled_per_capita.xml">Vehicle miles traveled per capita</a> gives the average number of vehicle miles traveled by each person in the specified geography. 
</p>
</related-indicators>

<how-modeled>
The value of this indicator is not directly modeled by Urbansim as it is based off of the results of the travel model, where vehicle miles traveled is calculated from. 
</how-modeled>

<limitations>
(1) Although this indicator can be computed at any geography, it is best to calculate it using all the data and obtain a single value. 
The reason it should only be cautiously used at any finer grained level of geography is because, for any vehicle trip that takes place, 
all the emissions produced on that trip is assigned to the unit of geography from which the trip originated. Consider this example: 
many people drive in from the suburbs to work downtown every work day. If calculated at the large-area geography, for example, it will look like greenhouse
gas emissions are being created mostly along the perimeters of the cities, in the suburbs, rather than being concentrated along major
highways and in the downtown region. This is caused by how vehicle miles traveled is calculated.

(2) Another limitation is that this indicator assumes that all vehicle miles traveled are taken in passenger cars--even those trips taken in light trucks, etc. On the otherhand,
it doesn't take into account more fuel-efficient cars like hybrids. As most vehicle travel is taken by passenger cars, using the typical passenger car as
a baseline for measuring vehicle emissions seems reasonable. 

(3) Emissions from busses and other forms of mass transit are not included in these calculations.
</limitations>

<source-evolution-examples>
This indicator was originally written by the UrbanSim group.
</source-evolution-examples>

<display-format>
<units>pounds of carbon dioxide (CO2) emitted</units>
<number digits="0"/>
</display-format>

</indicator-documentation>
<source>
<a href="http://trondheim.cs.washington.edu/cgi-bin/trac.cgi/browser/psrc/zone/greenhouse_gas_emissions_from_vehicle_travel.py">psrc.zone.greenhouse_gas_emissions_from_vehicle_travel</a>
</source>

</indicator-declaration>
