<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="doc-formatter.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE indicator-declaration SYSTEM "indicator-declaration.dtd">
<indicator-declaration display-name="Residential density">
<syntax-version-2.8/>
<indicator-documentation>

<definition>
This indicator gives the average number of residential units per acre of residential land for each year of interest in the selected geography.
</definition>

<interpreting-results>
See <a href="pop_density.xml#interpreting-results">Population density: Interpreting Results</a>.
(However, this indicator is in terms of residential units rather
than people, and gives the number of residential units whether occupied or not.)
</interpreting-results>

<specification>
First, we find the total number of residential units R. Then, we find the amount of the residential land L.  To do this,
for each grid cell we multiply
the number of acres per grid cell by the fraction of residential land for that grid cell, and sum the results.
The value of the indicator is then R/L. 
</specification>

<principal-uses>
This indicator is useful for both evaluative and diagnostic purposes.
</principal-uses>

<related-indicators>
<p>Other density indicators based on where people or jobs are located are 
<a href="pop_density.xml">Population density</a> and
Employment density.</p>

<p><a href="res_units.xml">Residential units</a> gives the total number of residential units rather than density.</p>

</related-indicators>

<limitations>
The code for this indicator computes the number of acres of
residential land in each grid cell as F times the number of acres per
grid cell, where F is the fraction of residential land for that cell.
F is only an approximation of the number of acres of residential
land in the cell -- F is computed by the residential land share component
of the Developer Model, which is based on real estate characteristics and does
not consider other features, such as water or roads, that might be partially
in the cell.  So if a cell is partially water or roads, generally this computation
will overestimate the number of acres of residential land in the cell, and so 
the value of this residential density indicator will be an underestimate (since the residential units
placed in the cell will actually be located within a smaller number of acres of residential land).
</limitations>
		
<source-evolution-examples>
This indicator was originally written by the UrbanSim group.
</source-evolution-examples>

<how-modeled>
This indicator is modeled by UrbanSim.
</how-modeled>

<display-format>
<units>residential units/acre</units>
<number digits="2"/>
</display-format>

</indicator-documentation>

<source>
<a href="http://trondheim.cs.washington.edu/cgi-bin/trac.cgi/browser/urbansim/gridcell/residential_density.py">urbansim.gridcell.residential_density</a>
</source>

</indicator-declaration>
