<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="doc-formatter.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE indicator-declaration SYSTEM "indicator-declaration.dtd">
<indicator-declaration display-name="Percentage of trips taken by bike">
<syntax-version-2.8/>

<indicator-documentation>

<definition>
This indicator gives a ratio of the number of trips taken by bike to the total number of trips taken overall.
</definition>

<interpreting-results>
Please see <a href="#how-modeled">How Modeled</a> for information on interpreting the results from this indicator.
</interpreting-results>

<principal-uses>
This indicator is useful for both evaluative and diagnostic purposes.
</principal-uses>

<specification>
The total number of bike trips taken over a year is divided by the total number of trips taken that year.
</specification>

<related-indicators>
<p><a href="mode_split_walk_trips_over_all.xml">Percentage of trips walked</a></p>
<p><a href="mode_split_sov_trips_over_all.xml">Percentage of trips taken in a single occupancy vehicle</a></p>
<p><a href="mode_split_carpool_trips_over_all.xml">Percentage of trips taken via carpool</a></p>
<p><a href="mode_split_transit_trips_over_all.xml">Percentage of trips taken on mass transit</a></p>
<p><a href="mode_split_park_ride_trips_over_all.xml">Percentage of trips taken as park and ride</a></p>
<p><a href="mode_split_bike_trips_over_all_excluding_walk.xml">Percentage of trips except walking taken by bike</a></p>
<p><a href="mode_split_human_powered_over_all.xml">Percentage of trips taken by bike or walked</a></p>
<p><a href="mode_split_carpooling_over_automobile_trips.xml">Percentage of automobile trips which are carpools</a></p>
</related-indicators>

<how-modeled>
UrbanSim currently uses an external travel model which, in the course of traffic modeling, generates "trips" from a source to a particular destination.
Although the model does not describe WHO is taking the trip, it does determine HOW and WHEN that trip is taken. There are seven trip modes that we consider: 
(1) walk, (2) bike, (3) single occupancy vehicle, (4) carpool with 2 people, (5) carpool with 3 or more people, (6) mass transit, and (7) park and ride.
The travel model generates a distribution of these modes of trips for the AM, Mid-day, and PM time periods. For the mode split indicators generated by UrbanSim,
trip time is not considered. Therefore, for each mode, the trip table for that mode is summed across all time periods. To calculate the mode split itself, each
trip mode that is part of the numerator for the ratio is summed, then divided by the sum of all trip modes that comprise the denomonator. For example, for the 
percentage of trips taken by bike is (all bike trips taken over all time periods) / (all trips by all modes taken over all time periods). 
</how-modeled>

<source-evolution-examples>
This indicator was originally written by the UrbanSim group.
</source-evolution-examples>

<display-format>
<units>none</units>
<number digits="0"/>
</display-format>

</indicator-documentation>
<source>
<a href="http://trondheim.cs.washington.edu/cgi-bin/trac.cgi/browser/psrc/zone/mode_split_bike_trips_over_all.py">psrc.zone.mode_split_bike_trips_over_all</a>
</source>

</indicator-declaration>
