<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="doc-formatter.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE indicator-declaration SYSTEM "indicator-declaration.dtd">
<indicator-declaration display-name="Nonresidential square foot value">
<syntax-version-2.8/>
<indicator-documentation>
<definition>
For each year of interest, this indicator shows the average value per square foot of nonresidential floorspace in 
each unit of geography.
</definition>

<interpreting-results>
This indicator is useful for seeing the average value per square foot of nonresidential floorspace in different 
parts of the region or in the region as a whole.
</interpreting-results>

<principal-uses>
This indicator is useful for both evaluative and diagnostic purposes.
</principal-uses>

<limitations>
<p>This indicator gives the <i>average</i> value per square foot of nonresidential floorspace 
over the specified geography.
UrbanSim does not model the land and improvement values of individual parcels, 
and therefore cannot provide a complete distribution of values, or 
statistics such as minimum and maximum values. </p>

<p>UrbanSim currently does not model demolitions of existing buildings, and
and demolished residential units or nonresidential space will continue to show
up in the database.  For example, if in a given year the Developer 
Model simulates the replacement of an older building with 5000 sqare feet of nonresidential floor space with a 
new building with 25,000 square feet, afterwards the UrbanSim database will include 30,000 square feet (representing
both the old and new building), rather than the correct value of 25,000.
This means that the average value per nonresidential square foot
may be lower than it should be in geographies that have experienced redevelopment.</p>
</limitations>

<specification>
For a given year, we first find the total nonresidential land value L by summing the nonresidential land values 
for all the grid cells in the unit of geography.
Then, we find the total nonresidential improvement value I by summing the commercial, industrial, and governmental
improvement values.
Finally, we find the total nonresidential square footage A by summing the commercial, industrial, and governmental 
square footage.  
The value of this indicator is then (L + I)/A.
</specification>
		
<source-evolution-examples>
This indicator was originally written by the UrbanSim group.
</source-evolution-examples>

<how-modeled>
This indicator is modeled by UrbanSim.
</how-modeled>

<display-format>
<units>monetary units, e.g., dollars</units>
<number digits="2"/>
</display-format>

<related-indicators>
<a href="nonres_sqft.xml">Nonresidential square feet</a> gives the total number of nonresidential square feet.  
</related-indicators>
		
</indicator-documentation>

<source>
<a href="http://trondheim.cs.washington.edu/cgi-bin/trac.cgi/browser/urbansim/gridcell/nonresidential_improvement_value.py">urbansim.gridcell.nonresidential_improvement_value</a>
</source>

</indicator-declaration>

