<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="doc-formatter.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE indicator-declaration SYSTEM "indicator-declaration.dtd">
<indicator-declaration display-name="Population density">
<syntax-version-2.8/>
<indicator-documentation>

<definition>
For each year of interest, this indicator gives the population density for residential land in the selected geography.
</definition>

<specification>
We compute the number of acres of
residential land in each grid cell as F times the number of acres per
grid cell, where F is the fraction of residential land for that cell.
Next, for the selected unit of geography, we calculate the total residential area R in that geography by summing the
residential area in each grid cell in that geography. 
Then we find the total number of people P in the geography, and calculate the indicator as P/R.
</specification>

<interpreting-results>
<p>A number of stakeholders want to foster compact development.
Such stakeholders will generally favor having compact, more densely populated neighborhoods
within the urban area, with very low density in the exurban and rural parts of the region (and in particular
little or no growth in these parts of the region).  As an indicator of compact development, the results from this 
indicator for user-defined or grid geographies are useful in showing the current status and trend.  
</p>
<p>When the selected geography is 'region,' results from this indicator don't
give any information on concentrations of population, but rather average the density for the whole region;
so in that case these results are useful mainly for understanding the operation of the 
models and diagnosing problems.  
</p>
</interpreting-results>

<related-indicators>
<a href="pop_in_compact_nbhds.xml">Fraction of population living in compact neighborhoods</a> gives
the fraction of the population living in neighborhoods with more than 12 people per acre.
Other density indicators based on where people or jobs are located are 
<a href="household_density.xml">Household density</a> and
<a href="employment_density.xml">Employment density</a>.
<a href="res_density.xml">Residential density</a> is based on residential units rather than households
(in other words, on buildings rather than people and jobs).
</related-indicators>

<principal-uses>
This indicator is useful for both evaluative and diagnostic purposes.
</principal-uses>

<source-evolution-examples>
This version was originally written by the UrbanSim group.
This indicator, displayed in map form, is similar to one used by 
<a href="http://www.northwestwatch.org">Northwest Environment Watch</a> as their key
indicator of sprawl in
<a href="http://www.northwestwatch.org/scorecard/">Cascadia Scorecard: Seven Key Trends
Shaping the Northwest</a>.  The Northwest Environment Watch indicator uses a somewhat
different calculation of population density, which is performed as follows.  Start with US Census block data.
Divide a metropolitan area into 30 x 30 meter pixels.
Calculate the population of each pixel, based on the block(s) of which it is a part.
(To do this, divide the 30x30 m pixel into n-squared "subpixels",
where n is typically 3.  Then, calculate the population of
that sub-pixel based on the population density of the census block that contains
the center of the sub-pixel.  Aggregate the 9 sub-pixel populations
into a single population value for the pixel.)
Then, around each pixel in the area being considered, draw a circle of radius
1 pixel.  If that circle contains 500 people, then stop.  Otherwise, increment
by one pixel, and keep going until the circle contains 500 people, or the land
area exceeds some fixed limit (calibrated so that the circle has &lt; .5 people
per acre).  Assign the population density of the smallest circle containing at least 500
people to the pixel at the circle's center.
</source-evolution-examples>

<limitations>
The code for this indicator computes the number of acres of
residential land in each grid cell as F times the number of acres per
grid cell, where F is the fraction of residential land for that cell.
F is only an approximation of the number of acres of residential
land in the cell -- F is computed by the residential land share component
of the Developer Model, which is based on real estate characteristics and does
not consider other features, such as water or roads, that might be partially
in the cell.  So if a cell is partially water or roads, generally this computation
will overestimate the number of acres of residential land in the cell, and so 
the value of this population density indicator will be an underestimate (since the persons
located in the cell will actually be living on a smaller number of acres of residential land).
</limitations>

<how-modeled>
This indicator is modeled by UrbanSim.
</how-modeled>

<display-format>
<units>persons/acre</units>
<number digits="2"/>
</display-format>

</indicator-documentation>

<source>
<a href="http://trondheim.cs.washington.edu/cgi-bin/trac.cgi/browser/urbansim/gridcell/population_density.py">urbansim.gridcell.population_density</a>
</source>

</indicator-declaration>
