<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="doc-formatter.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE indicator-declaration SYSTEM "indicator-declaration.dtd">
<indicator-declaration display-name="Residential units">
<syntax-version-2.8/>
<indicator-documentation>
<definition>
For each year of interest, this indicator shows the number of residential units in each unit of geography.
</definition>

<interpreting-results>
This indicator is useful for seeing the amount of available housing at different units of geography.  
(These residential units might or might not be occupied.)
</interpreting-results>

<principal-uses>
This indicator is useful for both evaluative and diagnostic purposes.
</principal-uses>

<limitations>
UrbanSim currently does not model demolitions of existing buildings, and
and demolished residential units or nonresidential space will continue to show
up in the database.  For example, if in a given year the Developer 
Model simulates the replacement of 4 older existing houses with a 20 unit
apartment building, afterwards the UrbanSim database will include 24
residential units, rather than 20.
</limitations>

<specification>
For the specialized 'region' version, we find all the grid cells exported for the given year, and sum the number of residential
units.  For the general form, for
each year and unit of geography, we find all the grid cells exported for that year that are in the geography.
Then we sum the number of residential units.
</specification>
		
<source-evolution-examples>
This indicator was originally written by the UrbanSim group.
</source-evolution-examples>

<how-modeled>
This indicator is modeled by UrbanSim.
</how-modeled>

<display-format>
<units>residential units</units>
<number digits="0"/>
</display-format>

<related-indicators>
<p>These results are for residential units, whether occupied or unoccupied.
<a href="vac_res_units.xml">Vacant residential units</a> gives the
number of vacant units.</p>
</related-indicators>
		
</indicator-documentation>

<source>
urbansim.gridcell.residential_units (Opus primary attribute)
</source>

</indicator-declaration>
