<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="doc-formatter.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE indicator-declaration SYSTEM "indicator-declaration.dtd">
<indicator-declaration display-name="Vehicle Miles Traveled per Capita">
<syntax-version-2.8/>

<indicator-documentation>

<definition>
This indicator gives a measure of the vehicle miles traveled per person on average during a given year.
</definition>

<interpreting-results>
Please see <a href="#how-modeled">How Modeled</a> for information on interpreting the results from this indicator.
</interpreting-results>

<principal-uses>
This indicator is useful for both evaluative and diagnostic purposes.
</principal-uses>

<specification>
Total vehicle miles traveled of trips starting in a particular zone divided by the number of people living in that zone. The mean of these values for the selected geography is returned.
</specification>

<related-indicators>
<p><a href="vehicle_miles_traveled.xml">Vehicle miles traveled</a> gives the total vehicle miles traveled with an origin in the specified geography. It is used in the calculation.</p>
<p><a href="population.xml">Population</a> gives the total number of people living in a particular geography. It is used in the calculation.
</p>
</related-indicators>

<limitations>
(1) Although this indicator can be computed at any geography, it is best to calculate it using all the data and obtain a single value. 
The reason it should only be cautiously used at any finer grained level of geography is because the measure doesn't make intuitive sense
between commercial, industrial, and residental areas. Consider this example: during a typical work day, many trips originate in downtown
(e.g. people going to lunch). However, not many people live in these downtown business districts; therefore, the vehicle miles traveled
per capita will be very high for that business district. Conversely, many people living in suburbs go to work downtown and take many trips
from there; the vehicle miles traveled per capita for the residental area will be much lower than the number of miles on average each of its residents
are actually taking. This bias is introduced because the underlying travel model doesn't model WHO is taking a trip, just whether a trip occurs
between two areas. This means that we cannot assign the mileage of a downtown lunch trip of a suburbanite to their respective residental geography,
as it is not explicated that it is actually that suburbanite taking the trip. (2) Busses and other forms of mass transit are not included in these calculations.

</limitations>

<how-modeled>
The value of this indicator is not completely modeled by Urbansim. Population is modeled by UrbanSim, while the vehicle miles traveled is obtained from the external travel model, Emme2.
</how-modeled>

<source-evolution-examples>
This indicator was originally written by the UrbanSim group.
</source-evolution-examples>

<display-format>
<units>miles per person</units>
<number digits="0"/>
</display-format>

</indicator-documentation>
<source>
<a href="http://trondheim.cs.washington.edu/cgi-bin/trac.cgi/browser/psrc/zone/vehicle_miles_traveled_per_capita.py">psrc.zone.vehicle_miles_traveled_per_capita</a>
</source>

</indicator-declaration>
